Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford records. 1976-2002 CPAA 86-30
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford records
1976-2002
Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford
CPAA 86-30
3 boxes (4.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
The Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford (PCCGH) was established in 1976 to promote and preserve Polish cultural heritage. The PCCGH is an affiliate member of the American Council for Polish Culture (ACPC). The club awards scholarships, participates in ethnic and multicultural events, and prepares displays and presentations about the history and literature of Poland. The collection illustrates a wide range of activities of the club from 1976 until 2002.
Historical Note
Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford (PCCGH) was formally established in 1976 and become an affiliate of the American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs, a nationwide organization established in 1948. American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs (ACPCC) changed its name to American Council for Polish Culture (ACPC) in November 1988; therefore both names are used within the collection. The main goal of PCCGH was to promote and preserve Polish culture and achievements of Poles to Polish American and American community. The club organized yearly events and participated in many state wide celebrations. One of the events, which attracted hundreds of people, is the Annual Szopka Festival, where school age children participated in a crèche making competition. The Club members assisted in preparation for the Polish Day at the Capitol which celebrated the anniversary of the Polish Constitution of May 3, 1791. Currently, many events that the club participates in promote Polish culture to wider global community and cooperates with the Connecticut Historical Society, and the World Affairs Council. PCCGH organizes events to attract younger audience by visiting local schools to talk and present ethnic history and art. The club also donates books on Polish history and literature to school and local libraries.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Material in the collection covers the years 1976-2002 and illustrates club activities and involvement in various events. The material contains minutes of meetings, newsletters, financial statements, and scrap books in addition to several photo albums documenting club activities from 1976 till 2003. The large portion of the material relates to the 40th Annual Convention of ACPCC, organized and hosted by the Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford in 1988. It includes also preparation material, convention programs and extensive reports and DVD's from performances at the convention.
The collection is open for research.
Initial donation of the material to the Connecticut Polish American Archives was made in 1986. In 1988 Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas donated material from the 40th ACPCC national convention which took place in Hartford, CT. The next donation of materials was made in 2000 and 2004 by Mrs. Ann Oleasz.
Search Terms
Polish Cultural Club of Greater Hartford; American Council for Polish Culture.; American Council of Polish Cultural Clubs.; Polish Americans - Connecticut.; Polish Americans - Connecticut - Periodicals.; Polish Americans - Societes, etc.; Minutes.; Reports.; Pamphlets.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Newsletter.; Photographs.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- PCCGH Celebrating 25 years, Anniversary booklet., 1976-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- PCCGH correspondence, reports, invitations., 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
- PCCGH calendar and activities book, (handwritten)., 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- PCCGH minutes, June - August., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- PCCGH newsletters., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- PCCGH correspondence., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- PCCGH President's report., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Young Americans of Polish Descent - bulletins and newsletter., 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- PCCGH correspondence with ACPCC national., 1981-1983x (Box 1, Folder 8)
- PCCGH cultural activities, correspondence, clippings., 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- PCCGH Poland Assistance Project., 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- PCCGH Szopka Festival - press releases, annual announcements, invitations., 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- PCCGH meeting notices., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- PCCGH cultural activities, clippings, flyers., 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- PCCGH correspondence, newsletter, minutes, events., 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13A)
- PCCGH correspondence., 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- PCCGH cultural events, clippings, pamphlets., 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- PCCGH newsletters., 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- PCCGH cultural events flyers, clippings., 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- PCCGH minutes, agendas, financial reports, convention guidelines., 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- PCCGH newsletter., 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- PCCGH cultural events, clippings, photograph., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- PCCGH board meetings minutes, financial reports., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- PCCGH financial information, minutes., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- PCCGH flyers, photos, cultural events., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- PCCGH newsletter., 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- PCCGH membership list., 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- PCCGH financial statements, agendas, board meetings., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- PCCGH clippings related to cultural events in Connecticut., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- PCCGH newsletter., 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- PCCGH reports, minutes, financial statements., 1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- PCCGH correspondence and cultural events, invitation., 1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- PCCGH correspondence regarding donation of books to various institutions in Poland., 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- PCCGH newsletter., 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- PCCGH letters received., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- PCCGH lecture notes, invitations for cultural events, clippings., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- PCCGH minutes, financial statements., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- PCCGH minutes, agendas, financial reports., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- PCCGH members survey, correspondence, cultural events flyers., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- PCCGH cultural events, clippings., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- PCCGH by-laws., 1989, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- PCCGH financial statements., 2001 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- PCCGH cultural events, brochures, clippings., 2001 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- PCCGH annual participation in Festival of Trees and Traditions., 1979-2001 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- PCCGH newsletter., 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- PCCGH minutes, financial statements., 2002 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- PCCGH Musical concert for the Golden Jubilee of SS. Cyril and Methodius church, Laura Grazyna Kafka a main performer, Hartford., May 2002 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- PCCGH cultural events, clippings., 2002 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Convention organizational meetings minutes., 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Convention Handouts., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Convention Agendas., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Convention Reports., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Convention Awards banquet and concert., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Convention Keynote Speaker - Mary Mazurek Heslin., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Convention Souvenir Book and program and speech by Prof. Stanislaus A. Blejwas., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Convention Workshops - programs, letters, notes., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Reception and exhibit at CCSU includes related correspondence, photographs, notes., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Post convention reports., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Franciszek Lachowicz letter on textbook errors on Poland distributed to some delegates at the convention., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Banner with John Paul II displayed at the Convention., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Convention bag with distribution pamphlets., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- 3 DVD's tapes:"Polish Theater in America" lecture by Jaroslaw Strzemien - Stas Radosh performance, pt.1; Stas Radosh performance, pt.2; Banner with Pope and short bio., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photo albums and scrap books covering various activities., 1976-2002 (Box 3, Folder flat)
- PCCGH - Distinguished Service Award for Janusz Bruks, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- PCCGH - Board minutes of meetings, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- PCCGH - Newsletter, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, budget, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, hotel agreement and payments, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, pre convention meetings and notes, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, publicity program, registration participants, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, banquet and ball program, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, Annual reports, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, official program, August 4-8, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, Marcalina Sembrich concert, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, thank you notes, photos, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- PCCGH - ACPC Annual 61st Convention in Hartford, Connecticut, convention material bounded, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 13A)
- PCCGH - donation to a scholarship fund, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- PCCGH - correspondence, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- PCCGH - check register from December 2009 to October 2010, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- PCCGH - board meetings and minutes, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- PCCGH - flyers, announcements, clippings, 2009-2011 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- PCCGH - Tragedy in Smolensk, clippings, notes, April 10, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 19)